Guide to the Lynne Sagalyn Research Files for "Power at Ground Zero" 1972-2016 MS 3128
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (PANYNJ), 1976-2015; 1.5 Linear feet
  - Commissioner Anthony Sartor voting record & related documents (2 folders), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Includes Sagalyn's 2015 log of Sartor's voting record, 2001-13, with underlying documents: Board material for Downtown Restoration Program, 2001-13, and Committee of Operations, 2009-14.
  - Transportation Phoenix (3 folders), 2002-2014 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-11)
    Sagalyn's notes, chronologies, news and articles log and analysis, with underlying source documents, related to Chapter 15.
  - WTC Transportation Hub documents (2 folders), 2003-2014 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Reports: "World Trade Center Assessment" and "World Trade Center Report: A Roadmap Forward", 2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Delivery problems (3 folders), 2008-2013 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15-17)
    Includes Sagalyn's chronologies, notes, article log, analyses, and interview notes, with underlying source documents, including among many others the Hub Working Group Steering Committee Final Report of September 25, 2008 and arbitration-related material.
  - WTC Tower 3, 2014 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes Sagalyn's notes and transcripts from Board meetings in 2014.
  - Net leases and financing, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Credit rating, 2006-2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial documents (2 folders), 1980-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4-5)
    Includes an audit of PANYNJ employee compensation plans (1980), audit report regarding toll increases (1981), PA Bus Terminal investment analysis (1999), financial statement for 2001, and official statement for Series UU notes (2003).
  - P8. Politics: PANYNJ, 1976-2015 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Press releases, 2003-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
- Series III. Lower Manhattan Development Corporation (LMDC), 2001-2016; 1 Linear feet
  The series includes materials that center on the development of downtown, most especially as it related to the role of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation (LMDC). Documents include press releases and other documents produced by or about the LMDC; planning and redevelopment-related documents, such as the World Trade Center General Project Plan (GPP)and Environmental Impact Statement (EIS); and Sagalyn's notes, chronologies, and other work product related to the source material.
  - New York City Department of City Planning (DCP) / Deputy Mayor Daniel Doctoroff, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - City Council Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment, 2006-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes Committee meeting briefing papers and summaries prepared by Sagalyn and research assistants.
  - Transcript of minutes of the City Council's Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment, 2006 March 9 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - LMDC Background, 2002-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    Includes by-laws, webpage and other print-outs of LMDC Board member biographies and other organizational information, and speeches by its executive officers. Also includes a list of LMDC Board minutes available online through 2011 and a CD labeled "LMDC minutes."
  - P13. Players: LMDC (3 folders), 2001-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - 130 Liberty Street deconstruction, 2003-2008 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    Includes overview, chronology and other material prepared by Sagalyn's research assistant. Includes a CD of documents downloaded by the RA, with a summary list in the file and some print-outs, including speeches and Committee briefing papers. See also Episode E16b in Series I.
  - P13b. Players: Lower Manhattan Construction Command Center (LMCCC), 2004-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    Includes notes from one interview, with other documents, mostly news articles.
  - LMDC press releases, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    Includes a few releases for 2002-05, and a log of releases for 2001-11 prepared by Sagalyn.
  - PP2. Plans & Planners: Process - General (2 folders), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - LMDC various documents (2 folders), 2002-2013 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3-4)
    Documents related to the performing arts/cultural center; a summary of community development block grants; LMDC/PANYNJ brochure re: design studies (2002); an agreement between the city and PANYNJ re: World Trade Center PILOT (payments in lieu of taxes) and re: design guidelines (both 2006); and various correspondence re: Sagalyn's requests.
  - LMDC Chronology: WTC Rebuilding Effort, 2001-2013 (2 folders), 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5-6)
    Includes Sagalyn's chronology, cross-referenced to source documents found in various files. This file holds certain documents from 2002-05.
  - World Trade Center General Project Plan (GPP). including amendments, and Environmental Impact Statement (EIS) materials (3 folders), 2003-2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - World Trade Center Generic Environmental Impact Statement (GEIS) (2 folders), 2004 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-11)
- Series IV. Commercial Real Estate and Silverstein Properties, 2001-2015; 1 Linear feet
  The series includes documents centered on the rebuilding of the World Trade Center towers, especially as it related to the involvement of developer Larry Silverstein and Silverstein Properties. Documents include agreements with Silverstein-related entities; media clips about Silverstein; and news articles, other published material, and presentations about commercial real estate and its economic prospects in lower Manhattan post-9/11.
  - 1 World Trade Center lease, 2001 July 16 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - P14. Players: Silverstein Properties. Various documents, 2002-2014 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes the interim access agreement between the Port Authority and various World Trade Center limited liability companies (LLCs), 2002; legal and other documents regarding leases and easements, 2003-07; news articles, 1987-13; public statements by Larry Silverstein; and Sagalyn work product, including notes, interview questions, and media log, 2001-14
  - Silverstein Properties. Media clippings and presentations (2 folders), 2005-2010 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14-15)
    Includes two packets of media clips from Silverstein Properties; slides of a presentation "Building for the Future" by John N. (Janno) Lieber of Silverstein; and a press packet, with CD, of materials titled "Completing the Vision" in connection with the unveiling of WTC designs by architects Norman Foster, Fumihiko Maki, and Richard Rodgers (2006).
  - World Trade Center deal realignment materials (2 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16-17)
    Includes NYC Economic Development Corporation's WTC Summary of Financial Analysis presentation to the City Council, with Sagalyn notes; letters from Silverstein properties to the Port Authority; the NYC Independent Budget Office's analysis of anticipated demand for space in a rebuilt WTC site; Port Authority board documents; master development agreement; and articles and Sagalyn media log.
  - RB5. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate (5 folders), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-5)
    Includes McKinsey's 2002 PowerPoint report "Revitalizing Lower Manhattan" to the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation; a report by Hugh F. Kelly for the Civic Alliance on downtown office prospects after 9/11; published reports by Cushman & Wakefield and others; and news articles/clippings.
  - RB5-1. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate: Freedom Tower / 1 World Trade Center (4 folders), 2004-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6-9)
    Includes a set of documents concerning the development and management of the 1 WTC observation deck, including the Request for Proposal (RFP) and lease with Legends Owo, LLC; Port Authority Board authorization of a joint venture with the Durst Organization; articles and clippings; and some Sagalyn and research assistant notes.
  - RB5-2 through RB5-5. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate: Sites 2, 3, 4, 5, 2006-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
- Series V. Rebuilding (RB) Files, 1983-2015; 1.5 Linear feet
  The series includes most of the thematic files designated with an RB prefix, or "rebuilding" files. These emphasize aspects of the rebuilding, whether of a specific place or infrastructure, or the broader environment of the area, such as the renewal of tourism. The files include newspaper articles (clippings, tear sheets, print-outs from newspaper websites or other on-line sources), miscellaneous primary and secondary materials (press releases, magazine articles), and some work product by Sagalyn.
  - RB3. Tourism, 1995-2012 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
  - RB4. Transportation (Mass transit, Hard rail). Reports, 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
  - RB4. Transportation. Infrastructure, 2001-2002, 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
    Includes news clippings and work product of Sagalyn and a research assistant.
  - RB4. Transportation (2 folders), 1993-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14-15)
    Includes Sagalyn and research assistant article abstracts and chronology, as well as many clippings and articles.
  - RB4-1. Transportation: Fulton Street Station, 2003-2007 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
  - RB6. Cultural (Freedom Center, Drawing Center), 2002-2012 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16)
  - RB7. Economics, including Lower Manhattan, 2002-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
    Includes, among clippings and other print matter, a CD of Sagalyn's 2005 paper/talk at the Wharton (UPenn) Real Estate Department on "The Politics of Planning the World's Most Visible Urban Redevelopment Project" and a CD of the 2002 Urban Land Institute fall meeting on "New York One Year Later."
  - RB8. Insurance; RB8-2. Litigation, 2002-2014 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - RB9. Incentives; RB19. Cost/Economics, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - RB10. 7 World Trade Center, 1984-2012 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - RB11. Skyscrapers, 1983, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes, among clippings and other documents, transcripts of panel discussions on "Building in the Aftermath of 9/11" held in 2002 at the National Buiding Museum.
  - RB14. Polls / C15. Commentary: Ballots, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  - RB15. Financing / Liberty Bonds (3 folders), 2002-2012 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6-8)
    Includes, with print matter, Sagalyn and research assistant work product including chronology and accounting of the $8 billion bond authorization.
  - RB16. Housing, 2002-2013 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
  - RB17. West Street, 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
  - RB18. Retail, 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
    Includes Port Authority Board documents related to joint venture agreements with Westfield America Limited Partnership and Westfield America Inc., with Sagalyn research assistant notes and other print matter.
  - RB22. Context: History, 2001-2012 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
  - RB25. Legal issues (other than insurance; includes allegations of fraud), 2004-2012 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Includes Sagalyn and research assistant work product summarizing World Trade Center disputes/litigation. Includes some print-outs of articles and CD of Summer 2010 WTC articles.
  - RB26. Security, 2001-2013 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
  - RB27. Environmental; RB29. WTC Utility Restoration & Infrastructure Rebuilding Program (as amended August 2004), 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
  - RB30. Construction Technical Achievements and Mishaps, including underground; RB39. Fiterman Hall, 2004-2015 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16)
  - Battery Park City Authority lease to Goldman Sachs Headquarters LLC, 2005 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
    Includes lease for development of trading and office space, as submitted with Goldman Sachs Form 8-K of August 23, 2005, with related documents.
- Series VI. Design and Memorial Materials, 1992-2016; 1.25 Linear feet
  The series includes materials regarding the process to design the World Trade Center 9/11 Memorial, including the perspectives of various concerned parties, such as the families of the deceased, and the considerations, such as historic preservation and the sanctity of the towers "footprint," involved in the design competition and outcome. The documents include advisory committee minutes and other primary documents. The series includes some thematic files related to the subject (E/Episodes; RB/Rebuilding; and ARC/Architectural Criticism & Commentary) that hold newspaper clippings, tearsheets, print-outs of articles, and the like. Some Sagalyn work product, such as chronologies, is in the series.
  - Various print matter, 2002 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes 4 documents: 1) New York New Visions, "Memorial Process Team Briefing Book: Findings from the Outreach, Temporary Memorials & Research Working Groups," March 2002; 2) APA NY Metro Chapter, "The Memorial Process: A Report of the Lower Manhattan Rebuild Task Force," Draft, May 14, 2002; 3) Daniel Libeskind, Leon Wieseltier, and Sherwin Nuland, "Monument and Memory," The Columbia Seminar on Art in Society, September 27, 2002 [edited transcript of a public program]; and 4) "Architecture and The Question of Memory: 2002 International Summer Design Studio and Conference on the WTC Memorial Design," Pratt School of Architecture
  - Memorial mission and Memorial process materials (binder content), 2001-2005, 2014 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes Sagalyn's working documents of the elements of the memorial process (2014) and various primary documents concerning public dialogue, including two transcripts of joint meetings of the Memorial Competition Jury and Families Advisory Council.
  - Memorial Foundation & LMDC Families Advisory Council (binder content) (2 folders), 2002-2013 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-4)
    Includes National 9/11 Memorial Foundation Board meeting minutes, LMDC Family Advisory Board and All Council meeting minutes, Memorial Center Advisory Committee materials, PANYNJ Board meetings relating to Memorial construction, agreements, press releases, and other documents.
  - Section 106 historic preservation and the World Trade Center site (binder content) (2 folders), 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Includes Sagalyn's chronology of WTC historic preservation/106 process(2014) and other research/work notes, with primary documents including the WTC Memorial and Redevelopment Plan Programmatic Agreement, memorandum of agreement between the Port Authority and various bodies regarding the WTC Transportation Hub, and other documents.
  - Sagalyn work product re: commentary on the Memorial, 2012 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
    Log of articles with key points and quotations summarized.
  - RB2. Rebuilding: Memorial, 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
  - RB12. Rebuilding: Historic preservation, 2001-2013 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    Includes, among other documents, material concerning the "survivors staircase," including a chronology prepared by Sagalyn and a research assistant.
  - E14. Episodes: Memorial design competition (2 folders), 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10-11)
    Includes, among other documents, a letter from architect Donald Woolery to Sagalyn with the description and drawings he had proposed for the WTC site.
  - E23. Episodes: Memorial redesign (3 folders), 2002-2016 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12-14)
  - E55-5. Episodes: Openings of rebuilt facilities: Memorial Museum, 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)
  - Curating the Memorial Museum, 2004-2014 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 16)
  - ARC2. Architectural Criticism/Commentary: NY Times: Herbert Muschamp, 1992-2004 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - ARC6. Architectural Criticism/Commentary: NY Times: Ouroussoff, Kimmelman, 2002-2011 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
  - ARC4 & 5. Architectural Criticism/Commentary: Other than New York Times (4 folders), 2000-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3-6)
  - ARC10. Architectural Criticism/Commentary: Book reviews, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
- Series VII. Players / Interests (P) Files: Public, Private, Civic, 1972-2016; 1.25 Linear feet
  The series includes most of the thematic files designated with a P prefix, or "players" files. These emphasize the various parties interested in the development of the site, including politicians, developers, businesses, civic organizations, the families of the deceased, and others. The files include newspaper articles (clippings, tear sheets, print-outs from newspaper websites or other on-line sources), miscellaneous primary and secondary materials (press releases, magazine articles), and some work product by Sagalyn.
  - Sagalyn work products, 2002-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
    Includes Sagalyn's log and notes on leadership articles in relation to the WTC (pertaining to chapter 4 of her book), log of articles by David Dunlap in the New York Times, and other and related documents.
  - P2. Politics: Pataki, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - P3. Politics: Spitzer; P4. Politics: U.S. Senators, 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
  - P5. Politics: State Level; P6. Politics: City Level (including Sheldon Silver); P26. Interests: New Jersey, 1972-2016 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
  - P7. Politics: Federal Aid (2 folders), 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - P9. Politics: MTA; P10. Politics: Collateral Issues; P11. Symbolic: Slurry Wall, Footprints, 2002-2010 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
  - P14. Developers: Larry Silverstein, including investment partners (4 folders), 1999-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14-17)
  - P15. Developers: Westfield, 2001-2013 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
  - P17. Interests: New York New Visions (NYNV), 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
    Includes the organization's by-laws (as amended November 2002), their booklet "Principles for the Rebuilding of Lower Manhattan" and a follow-on report "Possible Futures" by the Growth Strategies team, Executive Committee minutes for April-June 2005, and other documents.
  - P19. Interests: Civic Alliance to Rebuild Downtown New York, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
    Includes Economic Development Working Group Reports (2002); a statement of key principles for rebuilding; "Listening to the City" reports of proceedings for February and July 2002; the organization's response to the WTC Draft Generic Environmental Impact Study (DGEIS); and other documents.
  - P20. Interests: R.Dot (Rebuild Downtown Our Town), 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
    Includes meeting summaries.
  - P21. Interests: Municipal Art Society (MAS); PP6. Plans & Planners: Imagine New York (MAS), 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
  - P22. Interests: Labor Community Advocacy Network (LCAN); P23. Wall Steeet; P24. Business; P24S. Small Business, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
  - P25. Interests: Regional Plan Association (RPA); P27. Chinatown; P28. City Council, 1992-2009 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7)
  - P30. Interests: General (including unions and General Contractors Association); P31. The Families; P32. Downtown Residents (2 folders), 2001-2013 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - P33. Interests: Other Planning & Design Professionals, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
  - P36. Interests: Cultural Groups; P37. Media; P38. GMAC (bonds), 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
  - P39. Interests: NYC Department of City Planning; P40 Marriott (hotel leasholders); P43. Atheists, 1994-2011 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
- Series VIII. Other Thematic Files, 1985-2015; 1.75 Linear feet
  The series includes three sets of thematic files, including those designated with a prefix of PP ("plans and planners"), PE ("events/conferences"), and C ("commentary"). The Commentary files are the most extensive of these, and include copies of opinion and editorial pieces from, mostly, the New York City press, with Sagalyn's media logs and other related work product. Overall, the files include newspaper articles (clippings, tear sheets, print-outs from newspaper websites or other on-line sources), miscellaneous primary and secondary materials (press releases, magazine articles), and some work product by Sagalyn.
  - PP1. Plans & Planners: Players (Profiles) (8 folders), 1985-2015 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13-20)
    Articles by or about various people (mostly) and organizations, in alphabetical order, including Michael Arad, Elizabeth Berger, Brody Bond, Amanda Burden, Debra Burlingame, Santiago Calatrava, David Childs, Downtown Design Partnership (DDP), Alexander Garvin, Daniel Libeskind, George Marlin, Seth Pinsky, George Tamaro, Mary Ann Tighe, Lou Tomson, Peter Walker, John Whitehead, and several others.
  - PP3. Plans & Planners: Public Events (General); PP8. Conferences; PP9. Public Hearings, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 21)
  - PP4 & 5. Plans & Planners: Listening to the City (I & II), 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 22)
  - PP10. Plans & Planners: Historical Associations; PP12. Transportation Specifics, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 23)
  - PE1. Events/Conferences: Twin Beams of Light; PE2. Viewing Platform, 2002-2010 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1A)
  - PE3. Events/Conferences: Academic Conferences & Papers; PE4. Public Forums/Exhibits (third party), 2002-2011 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1B)
  - Event Notes (2 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2A-B)
    Includes transcripts of radio, TV and other public interviews; conference notes; and CDs of World Trade Center rebuilding events held at Cornell.
  - C1. Commentary: Editorials, New York Times, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - C2. Commentary: Editorials, Daily News, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
  - C3. Commentary: Editorials, New York Post, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - C4. Commentary: Editorials, Other New York/New Jersey Papers (2 folders), 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - C1-C4. Commentary: Editorials (various New York), 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 8)
  - C5. Commentary: Editorials, Non-New York; C6. Letters to Editor, New York Times; C7. Letters to Editor, Other, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9)
  - C8. Commentary: Op-Eds and Other Opinion Pieces (3 folders), 2000-2015 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10-12)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
  - C9. Commentary: Photojournalism; C10. Television/Video/Other; C14. Blogs, 2001-2012 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14)
  - Steve Cuozzo (NY Post) articles and related Sagalyn work product (analysis and log), 2002-2013 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
  - Sagalyn work product: editorial media logs and analysis (2 folders), 2009-2014 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Commentary on redesign of Freedom Tower and of 9/11 Memorial and related Sagalyn work products (2 folders), 2003-2012 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - "The Biggest Story", 2004-2008 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    Preliminary notes, outline and related for a chapter on the press and World Trade Center, subsequently integrated with other chapters in the book.
  - Lists of primary documents, 2012 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
- Series IX. Images and Diagrams, 2000-2016; .5 Linear feet
  The series includes various images of photographs, maps, diagrams, tables, editorial cartoons, and other graphic material, mostly in the form of reproductions (e.g., print-outs from the Internet, photocopies from publications, etc.). The images relate primarily to the various models and plans for the World Trade Center site and to scenes of Ground Zero and construction at the site. The series also includes those of Sagalyn's subject-oriented files that were designated with a "V" for visual imagery.
  - Imagery: V2. Artist Images; V3. Movies/Videos; V4. Computer Images; V5. Photos, 2000-2016 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8)
  - Images (7 folders), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 9-15)
  - "World Trade Center Site: Draft Transportation and Infrastructure Master Plan" (oversize), 2003 (Offsite-box 13)